AGENTS ASSEMBLE HACKATHON ù TECHNICAL PLAN
ContextMD
Intelligent Test Result Analysis & Clinical Briefing
Deadline: 12 May 2026  |  Team: [YOUR TEAM NAME]
1. The Problem
The Scene
A doctor opens a patient file. It contains:
  - 200 previous lab results spanning 5 years
  - 12 radiology reports
  - 8 specialist letters
  - 15 medications
  - 7 diagnoses from 4 different doctors
  - A new biopsy report that just came in 10 minutes ago
The doctor has 7 minutes with this patient.
They will read the new result. They will not read everything else.
They will miss context. Not because they are a bad doctor.
Because they are human, and the system gives them no choice.
The core problem is not the doctor. It is the absence of a system that connects a new result to everything already known about the patient and tells the doctor what it means in that specific context.
A sodium level of 128 means something completely different in:
A healthy 25-year-old athlete
A 70-year-old on diuretics with heart failure
A cancer patient currently on chemotherapy
Every test result needs to be read in the context of the whole patient. Right now, that context assembly happens inside the doctor's head, manually, under time pressure, with incomplete recall.
2. What ContextMD Does
Core Concept
Any new test result arrives ù blood test, biopsy, MRI report, ECG, pathology, surgical report.
ContextMD reads it, pulls the patient's entire FHIR history, cross-references medical literature,
and hands the doctor one intelligent briefing ù before they even open the file.
2.1 Input ù What Triggers the System
Any of the following can trigger ContextMD:
Result Type
Examples
FHIR Resource
Laboratory Results
Blood count, metabolic panel, tumour markers, hormone levels, cultures
Observation
Pathology / Biopsy
Cancer staging, tissue diagnosis, cytology
DiagnosticReport
Radiology Reports
MRI, CT, X-ray, ultrasound, PET scan findings
ImagingStudy + DiagnosticReport
Cardiac Tests
ECG, echocardiogram, stress test, Holter monitor
DiagnosticReport + Observation
Surgical Reports
Post-operative findings, intraoperative notes
Procedure + DiagnosticReport
Specialist Letters
Oncology, nephrology, neurology consult letters
DocumentReference
2.2 Output ù What the Doctor Receives
One structured briefing containing:
Section
Content
Result Summary
What the new result says, in plain clinical language ù no raw lab jargon
Patient Context
How this result fits into the patient's history ù trend over time, relevant past results, related diagnoses
Risk Assessment
What this result means for this specific patient given their conditions, age, medications, and history
Differential Considerations
What conditions this result is consistent with ù ranked by likelihood given the full patient picture
Recommended Next Steps
Top 3 actions ù further tests to order, specialist to refer to, treatment to consider
What NOT To Do
Contraindicated treatments given patient history, allergies, current medications, organ function
Relevant Literature
Latest clinical guidelines and trials relevant to this result and patient profile
Clinical Trial Eligibility
If applicable ù trials the patient may qualify for based on diagnosis and criteria
2.3 Clinical Scenarios Covered
Scenario
What ContextMD Does
Cancer diagnosis (new)
Reads pathology report, pulls staging indicators from imaging, cross-references oncology treatment guidelines (NCCN, ESMO), flags clinical trials, checks current meds for contraindications with chemotherapy agents
Cancer ù follow-up scan
Compares new scan to all previous imaging, identifies progression or remission trend, updates treatment recommendation based on response data
Pre-surgical assessment
Reads all relevant labs and imaging, checks anaesthesia risk factors (cardiac, renal, respiratory), flags anything that makes surgery high risk, produces pre-op summary for surgeon
Abnormal blood test
Compares to patient's full longitudinal lab history, identifies whether this is a new development or a worsening trend, checks medications that could cause this abnormality
Chronic disease monitoring
Diabetes HbA1c trend, kidney function trajectory, liver enzymes over time ù connects pattern to current treatment and recommends adjustment
Post-operative review
Reads surgical report and post-op labs together, flags early warning signs of complications, cross-references recovery guidelines for the specific procedure
Minor / routine result
Short clear summary ù result is within expected range given patient profile, no action required, or simple standard next step
3. Technical Architecture
3.1 Component Overview
Component
Type
Role
FHIR History Fetcher
MCP Tool 1
Fetches complete patient history ù all past results, diagnoses, medications, procedures
FHIR Result Ingester
MCP Tool 2
Reads and parses the new incoming test result from FHIR DiagnosticReport or Observation
FHIR Trend Analyser
MCP Tool 3
Fetches time-series data for specific tests ù builds longitudinal trend for any lab or vital
Literature & Guidelines Fetcher
MCP Tool 4
Queries PubMed, NCCN, NICE, ESMO APIs for relevant clinical guidelines and recent studies
Context Assembler Agent
A2A Agent
Pulls all MCP tool outputs together into a unified patient + result context object
Clinical Reasoning Agent
A2A Agent
Core AI reasoning ù interprets result in patient context, builds differential, assesses risk
Contraindication Checker Agent
A2A Agent
Checks proposed next steps against patient medications, allergies, organ function, prior reactions
Literature Synthesiser Agent
A2A Agent
Reads retrieved guidelines, extracts what is relevant to THIS patient's specific profile
Briefing Generator Agent
A2A Agent
Assembles final structured briefing ù one document, all sections, ready for doctor review
Orchestrator Agent
A2A Agent
Receives trigger, coordinates all agents in sequence, returns briefing to platform
3.2 Full Data Flow
New test result arrives in FHIR system
           |
           v
[Orchestrator Agent]  <-- triggered via Prompt Opinion platform
           |
           |-- parallel calls to MCP tools:
           |
           |-- [MCP Tool 1: FHIR History Fetcher]
           |       GET /DiagnosticReport?patient={id}
           |       GET /Observation?patient={id}
           |       GET /Condition?patient={id}
           |       GET /MedicationRequest?patient={id}
           |       GET /Procedure?patient={id}
           |       GET /AllergyIntolerance?patient={id}
           |
           |-- [MCP Tool 2: FHIR Result Ingester]
           |       GET /DiagnosticReport/{resultId}  (new result)
           |       Parses: result type, values, flags, performing lab
           |
           |-- [MCP Tool 3: FHIR Trend Analyser]
           |       GET /Observation?patient={id}&code={loincCode}&_sort=date
           |       Builds time-series: all previous values of same test
           |
           |-- [MCP Tool 4: Literature Fetcher]
                   PubMed API: search by condition + result type
                   NCCN / NICE / ESMO: guideline lookup by ICD-10 code
           |
           v
[Context Assembler Agent]
    Merges all MCP outputs into unified context object:
    { patient_profile, new_result, history, trends, guidelines }
           |
           v
[Clinical Reasoning Agent]  <-- core intelligence
    - Interprets new result in full patient context
    - Builds differential diagnosis list ranked by probability
    - Assesses clinical risk level: low / moderate / high / critical
    - Proposes top 3 next steps
    - Flags what NOT to do
           |
           v
[Contraindication Checker Agent]
    - Takes proposed next steps from Reasoning Agent
    - Checks each against: current medications, allergies,
      kidney function (GFR), liver function, prior adverse reactions
    - Returns: safe / modify dose / contraindicated for each step
           |
           v
[Literature Synthesiser Agent]
    - Takes retrieved guidelines and papers
    - Extracts only what applies to this patient's specific profile
    - Formats as 3-5 clinical references with relevance explanation
           |
           v
[Briefing Generator Agent]
    Assembles final doctor briefing:
    1. Result Summary
    2. Patient Context & Trends
    3. Risk Assessment
    4. Differential Considerations
    5. Recommended Next Steps (contraindication-checked)
    6. What NOT To Do
    7. Relevant Literature
    8. Clinical Trial Eligibility (if applicable)
           |
           v
Doctor opens patient file on Prompt Opinion platform
Briefing is already there. Ready to review.
3.3 SHARP Context Propagation
Every agent call and MCP tool call in the chain carries the SHARP context header ù patient ID, FHIR base URL, and access token. This means:
No agent re-authenticates separately
Patient scope never drifts between agent hops
MCP tools are generic ù they work for any patient, any hospital, any FHIR server
// SHARP header present on every MCP tool call
const sharp = JSON.parse(request.headers['x-sharp-context']);
// { fhir_base_url, patient_id, access_token, encounter_id }
const res = await fetch(`${sharp.fhir_base_url}/DiagnosticReport?patient=${sharp.patient_id}`, {
  headers: { Authorization: `Bearer ${sharp.access_token}` }
});
4. MCP Tools ù Deep Dive
These four tools form the Superpower layer. They are published to the Prompt Opinion Marketplace independently ù any other agent can call them.
4.1 Tool: get_patient_history
What It Fetches
Data
FHIR Resource
Fields Retrieved
All past diagnostic reports
DiagnosticReport
result type, status, date, conclusion, performer
All lab observations
Observation
LOINC code, value, unit, reference range, flag, date
Active & past diagnoses
Condition
ICD-10 code, display name, onset date, severity, status
All medications
MedicationRequest
drug name, RxNorm code, dose, frequency, start date, status
Procedures performed
Procedure
procedure name, date, outcome, performer
Allergies
AllergyIntolerance
substance, reaction type, severity, date recorded
Demographics
Patient
age, sex, weight, blood group
Output
{
  "patient": { "id": "7823", "age": 58, "sex": "female", "weight_kg": 72 },
  "conditions": [{ "icd10": "C50.9", "display": "Breast cancer", "onset": "2022-03" }],
  "medications": [{ "name": "Tamoxifen", "dose": "20mg", "frequency": "daily" }],
  "past_results": [{ "type": "CBC", "date": "2024-11", "summary": "WBC elevated" }],
  "allergies": [{ "substance": "Penicillin", "reaction": "anaphylaxis" }],
  "procedures": [{ "name": "Lumpectomy", "date": "2022-06", "outcome": "successful" }]
}
4.2 Tool: get_result
What It Does
Reads and parses one specific incoming DiagnosticReport or Observation from FHIR. Normalises the data into a clean structured object regardless of result type.
GET /DiagnosticReport/{resultId}
GET /Observation/{resultId}
Normalised output:
{
  "result_type": "Pathology",
  "test_name": "Core needle biopsy ù right breast",
  "date": "2026-05-01",
  "status": "final",
  "findings": "Invasive ductal carcinoma, grade 2, ER+, PR+, HER2-",
  "performing_lab": "City Hospital Pathology",
  "raw_fhir": { ... }
}
4.3 Tool: get_trend
What It Does
Fetches all historical values of a specific test for a patient, sorted by date. Used to build trend analysis ù is this getting better or worse over time?
// Example: trend for serum creatinine
GET /Observation?patient={id}&code=2160-0&_sort=date&_count=50
Output:
{
  "test": "Serum Creatinine",
  "loinc": "2160-0",
  "unit": "mg/dL",
  "values": [
    { "date": "2024-01", "value": 0.9, "flag": "normal" },
    { "date": "2024-06", "value": 1.1, "flag": "normal" },
    { "date": "2025-01", "value": 1.4, "flag": "high" },
    { "date": "2026-04", "value": 1.8, "flag": "high" }
  ],
  "trend": "progressively_rising",
  "change_over_period": "+100% over 28 months"
}
4.4 Tool: get_literature
What It Does
Queries medical knowledge sources for guidelines and research relevant to a specific condition and result type.
Data Sources
Source
API
What It Provides
PubMed
NCBI E-utilities API (free)
Recent peer-reviewed studies by condition + keyword
NCCN Guidelines
NCCN API / web fetch
US oncology treatment guidelines by cancer type
NICE Guidelines
NICE API (free, UK)
Evidence-based clinical guidelines ù any condition
ClinicalTrials.gov
ClinicalTrials API v2 (free)
Open trials patient may qualify for by condition + eligibility
RxNorm
NLM RxNorm API (free)
Drug information, interactions, normalised drug names
// PubMed search example
GET https://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/esearch.fcgi
    ?db=pubmed&term=invasive+ductal+carcinoma+ER+positive+treatment
    &retmax=5&sort=relevance&format=json
// ClinicalTrials eligibility search
GET https://clinicaltrials.gov/api/v2/studies
    ?query.cond=breast+cancer&query.term=ER+positive
    &filter.overallStatus=RECRUITING&pageSize=3
5. A2A Agents ù Deep Dive
5.1 Context Assembler Agent
Role
Takes the raw outputs from all four MCP tools and merges them into one unified context object that all downstream agents work from.
What It Produces
{
  "patient_profile": { age, sex, weight, conditions, medications, allergies },
  "new_result": { type, findings, date, performing_lab },
  "relevant_history": {
    "same_test_previous": [...],   // past results of same test type
    "related_results": [...],      // results related to same condition
    "relevant_procedures": [...]   // procedures relevant to this result
  },
  "trends": { "creatinine": {...}, "tumour_markers": {...} },
  "guidelines": [...],
  "clinical_trials": [...]
}
5.2 Clinical Reasoning Agent
Role
This is the core intelligence of the system. It takes the full context object and reasons about what the new result means for this specific patient.
Reasoning Steps
Interpret the result ù what does this finding mean clinically
Contextualise against history ù is this new, worsening, improving, or expected
Contextualise against conditions ù how does this interact with existing diagnoses
Build differential ù what conditions are consistent with this result given the full picture
Assess risk level ù low / moderate / high / critical ù with explicit reasoning
Propose next steps ù what should happen next, ordered by priority
Flag omissions ù what has NOT been done that guidelines say should be done
Risk Levels
Risk Level
Meaning
Example
Critical
Immediate action required
Troponin spike in patient with chest pain and prior MI history ù emergency referral
High
Action required within 24-48 hours
New cancer diagnosis ù urgent oncology referral needed
Moderate
Action required at next appointment
Rising HbA1c trend ù medication adjustment needed
Low
Monitoring only
Slightly low vitamin D ù supplement recommendation
5.3 Contraindication Checker Agent
Role
Takes every proposed next step from the Reasoning Agent and checks it against the patient's full safety profile before it reaches the doctor.
What It Checks
Check
Data Source
Example Flag
Drug-drug interactions
RxNorm Interaction API
Proposed anticoagulant conflicts with existing NSAID
Allergy conflicts
AllergyIntolerance from FHIR
Proposed antibiotic ù patient has documented penicillin anaphylaxis
Renal dose adjustment
GFR from Observation FHIR
Proposed drug contraindicated below GFR 30 ù patient GFR is 24
Hepatic considerations
LFTs from Observation FHIR
Proposed drug hepatotoxic ù patient has elevated ALT
Prior adverse reactions
AdverseEvent from FHIR
Patient had severe reaction to same drug class previously
Age-specific risks
Patient age + Beers Criteria
Proposed sedative ù high fall risk for patient aged 74
Output
{
  "next_steps_reviewed": [
    {
      "step": "Start carboplatin chemotherapy",
      "status": "safe",
      "notes": "No interactions with current medications. Renal function adequate."
    },
    {
      "step": "Add ibuprofen for pain management",
      "status": "contraindicated",
      "reason": "Patient GFR 24 ù NSAIDs contraindicated. Suggest paracetamol instead."
    }
  ]
}
5.4 Literature Synthesiser Agent
Role
Takes the raw literature retrieved by the MCP tool and filters it down to what is genuinely relevant to THIS patient. Not all guidelines apply to every patient.
Filtering Logic
Match guideline condition to patient's active diagnoses
Match patient age and sex to guideline eligibility criteria
Match result type to guideline scope ù e.g. post-surgery guidelines only if procedure recorded
Match clinical trial eligibility criteria against patient profile
Rank by recency ù prefer guidelines updated within last 3 years
Output
{
  "guidelines": [
    {
      "source": "NCCN Breast Cancer Guidelines v2.2025",
      "relevance": "Patient has ER+/HER2- invasive ductal carcinoma ù matches guideline scope exactly",
      "key_recommendation": "Adjuvant endocrine therapy recommended for 5-10 years",
      "url": "https://nccn.org/..."
    }
  ],
  "trials": [
    {
      "title": "monarchE ù Abemaciclib in early HR+ breast cancer",
      "status": "Recruiting",
      "patient_match": "ER+, node-positive ù patient meets primary criteria",
      "nct_id": "NCT03155997"
    }
  ]
}
5.5 Briefing Generator Agent
Role
Assembles all outputs from all agents into one clean, structured clinical briefing. This is what the doctor reads.
Briefing Structure
Section
Source Data
Format
Result Summary
MCP Tool 2 output
2-3 sentences, plain clinical language
Patient Context
MCP Tool 1 + Assembler Agent
Relevant history, how this compares to previous results
Trend Analysis
MCP Tool 3 output
Direction of change, time period, clinical significance
Risk Assessment
Reasoning Agent
Risk level (Critical/High/Moderate/Low) with explicit reasoning
Differential Considerations
Reasoning Agent
Ranked list ù most to least likely given full patient context
Recommended Next Steps
Reasoning + Contraindication Agents
Top 3 actions ù each marked Safe / Modified / Contraindicated
What NOT To Do
Contraindication Agent
Specific contraindications with reasons
Relevant Literature
Literature Synthesiser Agent
3-5 guidelines and studies with relevance explanation
Clinical Trial Eligibility
Literature Synthesiser Agent
Trials patient qualifies for ù title, status, match reason, NCT ID
6. Data Sources & APIs
6.1 FHIR Server
Environment
Server
URL
Development & Demo
HAPI FHIR Public Sandbox
https://hapi.fhir.org/baseR4
Production (future)
Hospital EHR via SMART on FHIR
Swap base URL and auth ù same MCP code works
6.2 All External APIs Used
API
Purpose
Cost
Endpoint
HAPI FHIR
Patient data ù all FHIR resources
Free
https://hapi.fhir.org/baseR4
NCBI PubMed E-utilities
Medical literature search
Free
https://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/
ClinicalTrials.gov API v2
Open clinical trials search
Free
https://clinicaltrials.gov/api/v2/studies
NICE Evidence API
UK clinical guidelines
Free
https://api.nice.org.uk/
RxNorm Interaction API
Drug-drug interactions
Free
https://rxnav.nlm.nih.gov/REST/interaction/
NCBI LOINC Lookup
Lab test code normalisation
Free
https://lhcforms.nlm.nih.gov/api/
OpenFDA
Drug adverse events, labels
Free
https://api.fda.gov/drug/
6.3 FHIR Resources Used
FHIR Resource
What We Use It For
Patient
Demographics ù age, sex, weight
Condition
All diagnoses ù ICD-10 coded, onset date, status
Observation
Lab results, vitals ù LOINC coded, values, trends
DiagnosticReport
Full test reports ù pathology, radiology, cardiology
MedicationRequest
All active and historical medications
AllergyIntolerance
Allergies and adverse reactions
Procedure
Past surgeries and procedures
ImagingStudy
Radiology study metadata
AdverseEvent
Prior adverse drug reactions
DocumentReference
Specialist letters, unstructured clinical documents
7. Open Questions for Team
Question
Options
Recommendation
MCP server language?
Node.js vs Python
Node.js ù faster dev, better MCP SDK
How to parse radiology reports?
Trust DiagnosticReport text field vs run NLP over it
Trust FHIR text field for demo ù NLP is V2
LLM for reasoning agent?
Claude API (via Anthropic) vs GPT-4o
Claude ù we are on their platform
Which demo patient?
Find on HAPI FHIR sandbox
Pick a cancer patient with 2+ years of history and multiple result types
Literature depth?
PubMed only vs PubMed + NCCN + NICE
PubMed + NCCN for demo ù most impressive combo
Trigger mechanism?
Doctor manually pastes result ID vs auto-detect new results
Manual paste for demo ù simpler and controllable
Every result means something different. We know the difference.
